Okay, so in this video then, we are going
to talk about decision trees.
Decision trees use as EMV, expected
monetary values, right, to come up with a
decision, to make a decision about your
project.
All right, so this is a typical type of
question that you could get on the exam.
And then based on this question,
we are going to create a decision tree.
Okay.
All right, so let's first read the
question here.
So it says here, you're deciding to build
a new plant or upgrade an existing plant.
Building a new plant will cost $200
million.
Upgrading will cost $80 million.
Either way, there's a
65% chance of getting a
strong demand and a 35%
chance of a weak demand.
If you build and you get a strong demand,
you will make 320 million.
Otherwise, if you have a weak demand,
you will make 150 million.
If you upgrade and have a strong demand,
you will make $190 million, otherwise you
will make $95 million if you have a weak
demand.
What are the EMVs to build and upgrade and
which option should you choose?
Okay, all right, so there's a lot of
numbers in this question.
There's numbers all over the place.
So the first thing we want to do is we
want to organize.
I want to organize these numbers.
Understand what these numbers actually
mean, right?
Where are these numbers coming from?
or rather, where are these numbers going
more than anything else?
And that's where decision tree is coming.
So the first thing we need to recognize is
that, you know, we're making a decision,
that this is a decision tree question.
And basically it tells us at
the beginning, says you're
deciding to build a new plant
or upgrade an existing plant.
And it's also saying right at the end,
which option should you choose?
So first up then, we have to come up with
our decision.
What is our decision?
So, our decisions are, either we build or
we upgrade.
That is our decision.
We either build or we upgrade.
Right.
And then it says in the second paragraph,
or rather in the second sentence,
it says, building a new plant will cost
$200 million.
Upgrading will cost $80 million.
So our decision then, if we build,
it's going to cost $200 million.
And it's a negative number.
It's a cost.
Therefore, it's a negative number.
If we build, it'll cost $200 million.
However, if we upgrade, it says it'll cost
$80 million.
So upgrading is going to cost $80 million.
Now, if that was our only consideration,
then obviously, we would upgrade.
Why would we build for $200 million when
we can upgrade for $80 million?
However, that's not our only consideration
because now one of two things can happen.
And these one of two things are known as
uncertainties, or they could
be called chance, right?
Uncertainties or chance.
So what's our uncertainty?
Well, in the next sentence, it says either
way, so whether we build or whether we
upgrade, either way, there's
a 65% chance of getting
a strong demand and a 35%
chance of a weak demand.
So that's how we're uncertain to then.
Either we get a strong demand or we get a
weak demand.
So, and it says either
way, so if we build, we
can get a strong demand
or we get a weak demand.
And it says either way, whether we build
or we upgrade.
If we upgrade, we either get a strong
demand or we get a weak demand.
And it tells us, it tells in the question,
if we get a strong demand, there's a 65%
chance or rather, there is
a 65% chance of getting a
strong demand and a 35%
chance of getting a weak demand.
So either way, strong is 65%, weak is 35%.
So whether we build or whether we upgrade.
Now, don't worry about what strong demand
or weak demand actually means.
Don't get hung up by the meaning of these
terms.
It's just a scenario they've given to in a
question.
Okay, now, the next sentence then says,
if you build and you get a strong demand.
So now we're looking at one branch at a
time.
If we build and we get a strong demand,
it says we are going to make $320 million.
So if we build and we get a strong demand,
we'll make $320 million.
And it's a revenue, therefore it's a
positive number.
Otherwise, if you have a weak demand,
we'll make $150.
If we get a weak demand, we'll make $150
million.
And then it says here, again, in the next
sentence, if you upgrade, if we upgrade,
and we get a strong demand, we're going to
make 190 million.
Otherwise, if we get a weak demand,
we're going to make 95 million,
as it says here.
Right, we're going to make 95 million.
So everything that we have written up here
so far, right, on this decision tree,
this has all been given to us in the
question.
We have all of these values.
They're all here in the question.
Now, we haven't done any math yet.
So, when you're reading
the question, it just,
initially, it just seems
very daunting, right?
Got these numbers all over the place.
But the main thing about decision tree is
break these numbers down, right?
Organize these numbers.
And that's really all we're doing in this
decision tree.
All we've done is organize these numbers.
So now that we've got these numbers,
now we can figure out our EMB,
and then we can figure out whether to
build or whether to upgrade.
Now, also, let's look at this,
though.
If we build and we get a strong demand,
we're going to make $320 million.
If we upgrade and we get a strong demand,
we're only making $190 million.
If we build and we get weak demand,
we'll make $150 million.
But if we upgrade, we'll only make $95
million.
So looking from a purely revenue
perspective, well, we would want to,
you know, we'd probably want to build
because we're getting much more revenue,
right, in building.
than we are in upgrading, but when we're
looking at the cost perspective,
right, we would rather upgrade than build
because upgrade is costing a lot less.
So we want to take all of
these into consideration, and
that's the reason why we
perform these decision trees.
All right, so we're going to use EMV,
expected monetary value, right,
to figure out, should we build or should
we upgrade?
How do you calculate EMV?
Right, well, probability times impact.
They've given us a probability in the
exam, they will always give a probability,
65%, 35%, I mean, they don't, it doesn't
always have to be, obviously 65,
35, but they will always give it the
probability.
We first have to figure out the impact,
what is the impact.
So what we have here is a revenue and a
cost situation.
So our net impact then in this case is
going to be really our profit, our return.
So if we build and we have a strong demand
and we're going to do an EMB for each of
the four branches, if
we build and we get a
strong demand, we're
going to make 320 million.
So we get a strong demand,
we're going to make 320 million,
but we'll have spent $200
million in actually building.
So what's our net profit in this case?
Right, well, 120 million.
The 320 million minus a 200 million, we
are going to make a profit of 120 million.
However, that's not guaranteed,
right?
There's a 65% chance of that happening.
So 65% then of 120 million, the EMV is 78
million.
Now that's our EMV, if we get a strong
demand.
However, we may not get a strong demand.
We may end up with a weak demand instead.
Only one of these two things can happen.
Either we get a strong demand or we get a
weak demand.
If we get a weak demand, we'll only make
150 million.
We'll have still spent $200 million.
Right, we're going to spend $200 million
in building.
Either we get a strong
demand and make $120
million, or we end up with a weak demand.
We make a revenue of $150.
So what's our net impact now?
Well, make a loss, negative $50 million.
We may end up potentially making a loss
now with $50 million, right, which is
basically the $150,000 minus the cost 200
million and there's a 35% chance of that
happening so 35% then of negative 50 is
negative 17.5 million dollars so that's a
major consideration to make now we may end
up actually making a loss if we if we
build and so now we do exactly the same
calculations for the upgrade branch if we
get a strong demand we're going to make
190 million but we'll have spent 80
million in upgrading so what's our net
impact now net profit 110 million dollars
and there's a 65% chance of that happening
so 65% of 110 million is 71.5 million
dollars 7.1 million five million dollars
if we end up with a weak demand though
we're going to make 95 million but we'll
have spent 80 million in upgrading and so
our net impact 15
million right we're going to
make 95 million 95
million minus the 80 million.
And the 35% chance of that happening.
Again, the percentages are given to us in
the question here.
And so the total EMV then 5.25 million.
So now we want to look at the total EMV
for build and for upgrade.
So if you look at build, the 65% EMV is 78
million.
The 35% EMV is 17.5 million.
So the 100% EMV, the total EMV,
for building, you add them up.
You have to add them up.
Or subtract, cost one is negative.
So the total EMV then is
going to be the 78 million
minus the 17.5 million or
plus negative 17.5 million.
And so it's $60.5 million.
Do the same thing with the upgrade.
With the upgrade branch.
The strong EMV, right, the 65%
EMV, if we get a strong demand, it's 71.
5 million.
that we calculated, the weak demand,
the 35% EMV is 5.25 million.
And so the 100% EMV add those two together
and you get 76.5 million.
So what's the answer?
What should we do?
So the question is, what are the EMVs to
build an upgrade?
So these are the EMVs to build an upgrade.
Which option should we choose?
Well, naturally, we would, in this case,
we would upgrade.
Because potentially we're getting the
higher return.
So that's generally how you calculate
decision trees.
Now what do we do with these numbers?
Well, we don't really do anything with
them.
It's not like the EMV calculation that we
talked about in a previous slide,
where we would take the
total EMV and then make
some adjustments to
our contingency result.
Here, we're just using these to make a
decision.
That's it.
It's just purely and simply for decision
making.
So in the exam then, as I said,
they'll always give you, probability they
will always give you the impact I mean
they'll always give a probability they'll
always give you all these numbers you just
literally have to first of all figure out
what the net impact is and then multiply
with the probabilities okay so here this
is a very very simple
example a typical example of a
decision tree type of question
that you could get on the PMP